Guide to the Alfredo Castaneda Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Alfredo Castaneda papers
1972-1980
SC0268
Castañeda, Alfredo
11 Linear feet
These papers pertain to Castaneda's teaching career at Stanford and include correspondence, student papers, reports, publication files, and course materials. Subjects include his professional and teaching activities, his students, bilingual education, and Mexican Americans. The papers also include minutes from seminars held at the Boys Town for the Study of Youth Development at Stanford, 1975-76 (subsequently known as the Stanford Center for the Study of Youth Development).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Transferred by School of Education, 1981.
Information about Access
Partially restricted: confidential student files not open.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Alfredo Castaneda, a nationally prominent expert in multicultural education, was professor of education at Stanford from 1972 until his death in 1981. He was the first Chicano appointed full professor at Stanford. Castaneda received his a.b. from San Francisco State in 1948 and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Ohio State in 1951 and 1952. Prior to his appointment at Stanford, he taught at several universities including the University of Toronto, Queens College of the City University of New York, the University of Texas, and the University of California at Riverside, where he had been chairman of Mexican- American Studies.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain to Castaneda's teaching career at Stanford and include correspondence, student papers, reports, publication files, and course materials. Subjects include his professional and teaching activities, his students, bilingual education, and Mexican Americans. The papers also include minutes from seminars held at the Boys Town for the Study of Youth Development at Stanford, 1975-76 (subsequently known as the Stanford Center for the Study of Youth Development).
Some student files contained materials of a sensitive nature. These have been separated from the rest of the collection in Box 8 and are not open to researchers.
Access Terms
Boys Town Center for the Study of Youth Development.; Castañeda, Alfredo; Stanford Center for the Study of Youth Development.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Curricula.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Education, Bilingual --United States.; Mexican Americans--Education.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Ortiz, Lupe (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Solit, Lizz Campos (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation Advisees (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dissertations:, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dissertations:, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Affirmative Action at Stanford: Policies, 1972-73 Report, 1973-74 Priorities (Box 1)
  - Study Guideline of the History and Culture of the Mexican American (Box 1)
  - Barbieri, Paolo (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Palo Alto Unified School District (1979) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research Group: Inter-ethnic Relations Research Group (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research Assistantships 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development and Education (Ramirez and Castaneda) (Box 1)
  - Bilingual Education Paper Series: The Title VII (Bilingual Education) Fellowship Program: A Preliminary Report (4 copies) (Box 1)
  - Bilingual Educ. -Crt. & Educ. Acts (Lau vs. Nichols) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bilingual Educ. -Curriculum Models Spanish-Speaking Migrant Students (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorandum: January 6, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Book: Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development & Education by A. Castaneda and M. Ramirez, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Book: Mexican Americans and Educational Change (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book Orders, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brazilean Project -Vince Martin, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1973-74 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Practicum for the MA Program in Cultural Pluralism -A. Castaneda (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dissertations -1975 -77 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Research, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ramos, Robert -A.T.&T., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Poems (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Pottinger, Stan (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Administrative Correspondence regarding Advisees ..., 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Various student papers (Education 180,214,242,381), publications, articles, Biocognitive Inventory Forms (adult, student, teacher), dissertations, Bibliographies for classes, References for Bilingual Education Title VII (Box 2)
  - Meadowcroft, Jean (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Orals (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Schedule of Classes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fountenberry, Carolyn (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Flores, David (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fortman, Maurice (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dr. Castaneda (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lamb, Gene (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Harvard Journal on Chicano Affairs (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Harvard University Press Nat'l Advisory COuncil (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Meetings: Chicano (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - La Red!fhe Net Monthly Newsletter (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Farwest Laboratory for Ed'l Research and Development 1973-74 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ford Foundation, 1973-75 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Memos, Bulletins, & Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Navarro, Susan (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Parker-Ware, Robin (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lopez, Alonso (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bilingual Association of Students Materials (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bilingual-Bicultural Education (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jr. High Midsites & Participation (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Garcia, Angie (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Gorrez, Lydia (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Relation of Stress and Differential Position ..... Motor Learning (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Response to Conflict as a Function of Response-Defined Anxiety (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clash of Cultures in the Classroom (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Description of a Program to Train Parents to Influence the Development of (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Question-Asking Skills in their Young Children, by Angela Garcia (Box 3)
  - Grand Jury Report: San Francisco Unified School District (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Student papers, proposals, dissertations, teaching guidelines (Box 3)
  - Student Papers (#19 - 23) 1972-77 Boys Town Center for the Study of Youth Development (seminar minutes 1975- 1976 and materials on search for director 1974) (Box 4)
  - Student Papers (#10 -18) (Box 5)
  - Student Papers (#1 -9) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and articles for Education students (Box 7)
  - Associative Strength and Degree of Learning Competition in Verbal Paired-Assoc. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Complex Learning and Perfomance as a Function of Anxiety in Children and Task Difficul ty (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Differential Relation of Latency and Discrimination Response Vigor to Stimulus .... Brightness (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Education Needs of Mexican Americans (Box 7)
  - Melting Potters vs. Cultural Pluralists (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Melting Potters vs. Cultural Pluralists (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Castaneda, Alfredo: Melting Potters vs. Cultural Pluralists (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Castaneda, Alfredo: Melting Potters vs. Cultural Pluralists (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Sex Differences, Sex Typing, and Women's Studies Bibliography (Box 7)
  - Anxiety and the Differential Adaptation Hypothesis (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Notebook: Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development & Education I-IV (Box 7)
  - Notebook: Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development & Education V-VIII (Box 7)
  - Cultural Democracy, Bicognitive Development & Education I-VIII (Box 7)
  - The Book of Readings (Box 7)
  - Symposium: Mexican Americans and Educational Change (Box 7)
  - Nat'l Committee on the Education of Migrant Children (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chicanismo (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Nuestra Lucha (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Assm. of Police-Comm. Relations: Toward Quality Education for Mexican Americans (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Student papers
    Restricted for 75 years from date of creation.
    - Bianchi, Maria (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Calzada-Cota, Irene (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Delgado, Terre (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Fernandez, Celestino (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Gallardo, Edgar (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Garcia, Ron (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Hernandez, Francisco (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Menchaca, Isaias (2/75) (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Martinez, Ben (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Ramirez, David (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Ratliff, Shirley (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Valenzuela, Anna Marie (Box 8, Folder 12)